Guide to the Pimp C rap artist collection, 1987-2008 MS 651
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Pimp C rap artist collection
1987-2008
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Butler, Chad "Pimp C"
MS 651
3 Linear Feet 2 boxes
0.869 Gigabytes video concert performance footage and interview, nearline MS0651aip_001
5.25 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0651aip_002 (5.25 GB)
The Pimp C rap artist collection includes several documents and promotional items including handwritten lyrics and contracts to promotional flats for his group Underground Kingz (UGK).
Biographical Sketch
Chad "Pimp C" Butler was a founding member of the rap group Underground Kingz (UGK) along with Bernard "Bun B" Freeman in 1987 in Port Arthur, Texas. They released their first album "Too Hard to Swallow" in 1991. In 2000, they were nominated for a Grammy for Best Rap Performance by a Duo or Group for "Big Pimpin" with Jay-Z. In 2002 Pimp C was arrested for violating his probation, stemming from an aggravated assault charge, and sentenced to eight years in prison. On December 30, 2005, Pimp C was released from prison and placed on parole. By July 11, 2006, he released his first solo album "Pimpalation." He reunited with Bun B and by 2007 released the first UGK album since his release from prison titled "Underground Kingz." Pimp C passed away in his hotel room on December 4, 2007. After his death Bun B released the final UGK album "UGK 4 Life," in which most of the recording was finished before Pimp C's death.
See online video clip "Pimp C: Real Legends Live On" at https://youtu.be/fr1XJDtGLdo. "In this mini doc shot in 2017 for Pimp C's posthumous induction into the CERCL Hip Hop Archival Collection at the Woodson Research Center in Rice University's Fondren Library, some of hip hop's royalty speak on the influence Chad Lamont 'Pimp C' Butler had on them and the hip hop culture."
Content Description
The Pimp C rap artist collection contains several documents and other paraphenalia of the artist Chad "Pimp C" Butler. The documents include handwritten song lyrics on loose leaf paper and cardboard, papers from the Texas Department of Justice relating to his arrest for aggravated assault, a Grammy nomination, a copy of his obituary from his funeral, and a marketing plan by FM2 Radio and the joint venture deal with Universal Music Group. Also included in the collection are several forms of artwork featuring Pimp C and a 12-inch record (warped), with the songs Stop-N-Go and The Game Belongs to Me.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated by Chinara Butler and Corey Garrett, through the Center for Engaged Research and Collaborative Learning (CERCL) at Rice University.
Related Materials
Please see the dissertation by Charles Clark III "The Birth of Country Rap Tunes" ML3531.C62 2019. To see his accompanying presentation, you can request access to digital object MS0651aip_002.
Index Terms
Subjects
African Americans; Rap (Music); Music; Art
Document Types
notes; contracts; legal documents; digital moving image formats
Places
Texas -- Houston
- Series I: Lyrics, ca. 1987
  - Unfinished song lyrics (Tennessee Texas), Untitled handwritten fragment beginning "Everythang everythang when you know yo place"; Notebook of lyrics, Lyrics on cardboard, ca. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Series contains unfinished lyrics from Tennessee Texas on pieces of loose leaf paper, lyrics written on a piece of cardboard, and a wide-ruled notebook with several pages of lyrics written on them.
- Series II: Contracts, 2006
  - Marketing Plan by FM2 Radio & UGK Records Inc. with Universal Music Group joint venture deal, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Strategic marketing plan put forth by FM2 Radio including a contract from Provident Financial Management who handledthe financial planning and management of Chad Butler's career and estate. Also included is the joint venture deal betweenUGK Records Inc. and Universal Music Group.
- Series III: Texas Department of Criminal Justice Papers, 2006
  - Special Conditions and Temporary Travel Permits, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Forms from the Texas Department of Criminal Justice including: notice of special conditions (urinalysis monitoring) and temporary travel permits to Atlanta, GA; Jackson, MS; Nashville, TN.
- Series IV: Obituaries, 2007-2008
  - Chad "Pimp C" Butler Obituary, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Obituary from the funeral service of Chad "Pimp C" Butler held in Port Arthur, TX.
  - The Source Magazine (R.I.P. Pimp C cover), 2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Copy of the February 2008 edition of The Source magazine. The magazine features Pimp C on the cover and features an article about the life of Pimp C.
- Series V: Documents
  - Business Cards (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Credit card style business cards for Pimp C, includes an email address and MySpace information.
  - Naked Soul of Sweet Jones Spreadsheet, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Spreadsheet of the song list from the album Naked Soul of Sweet Jones which was released posthumously by Pimp C on October 5, 2010.
- Series VI: Artwork, undated
  - Wooden artwork of Pimp C (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stencil drawing of Pimp C, framed (Box 2)
    Framed stencil drawing of Pimp C
- Series VII: Oversize and realia
  - Dirty Money Flats, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Promotional flats for Underground Kingz Dirty Money (x2)
  - Big Pimpin Grammy Nomination, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Grammy nomination certificate for Underground Kingz (UGK) for best rap performance by a duo or group for "Big Pimpin" (with Jay-Z) for the 2000 Grammy Awards.
  - Port Arthur Resolution, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Resolution signed by Mayor Deloris Prince of Port Arthur in 2007 after the death of Chad "Pimp C" Butler.
  - "Long Live the Pimp" dice (clear acrylic, with white ink) (Box 2, Envelope 4)
  - Underground Kingz 33rpm LP record (warped), 2006 (Box 2, Folder -)
    12-inch record (warped) of Stop-N-Go and The Game Belongs To Me by Underground Kingz (UGK). The record was intended for promotional use only and has clean, dirty, and instrumental versions of both songs.
  - Underground Kingz pencil drawing, 48"x52" (Drawer 35)
  - Pimpalation flats (2), circa 2006 (Drawer 35)
- Series VII: Concert performances and interview, 1996-2007
  - Underground Kings interview in Baton Rouge 1996 and concert in Houston TX 2007 (filename: ugkint'96&concert'07.mov), 0.0564 Gigabytes 12 minutes
    General
    1996 interview of UGK in Baton Rouge and a concert in Houston TX 2007
    Interview 0:00 to 4:45. good sound quality, seems to stop in mid interview and cut to concert.
    concert 4:46 - 12:06. concert footage does not have sound
  - Underground Kings and Jay Z performing Big Pimpin at Los Magnificos Custom Car Show in Houston, TX 1999 (filename: bigpimpinlive'99.mp4), 0.0278 Gigabytes 3 minutes
    1999 performance of Big Pimpin - UGK and JayZ performing Big Pimpin at Los Magnificos Custom Car Show in Houston, TX. Video shows performers onstage, sound includes the crowd more than the performers. 3 minutes, 5 seconds in duration.